Okay,
so today is צדיק ח', Tzadik Chet, עמוד א'. Amud Aleph. We
are about the middle of the page, I would say about ten
wide lines down at the two dots.
So the גמרא Gemara quotes a פסוק, Pasuk, y'all have it, ועלהו
לתרופה. Va-alehu li-trufa. The line begins with the word מתניו Matnav and
it's in the middle of the line. Okay,
so we had just discussed this is coming out of left field,
this next statement, but we had just discussed a dispute between רב
חסדא Rav Chisda and רב יצחק בר אבדימי. Rav Yitzchak bar Avdimi.
So here's another dispute between רב חסדא Rav Chisda and רב יצחק
בר אבדימי. Rav Yitzchak bar Avdimi. The פסוק Pasuk says in, is
it in יחזקאל Yechezkel also? Yeah. ועלהו לתרופה. Va-alehu li-trufa. So it's
a Messianic vision of a river coming out of גן עדן Gan
Eden I think, or no, coming out of the קודש הקודשים, Kodesh
Hakodashim, coming out of the מקדש, Mikdash, and there's trees growing on
it. It's one of these idyllic visions of the Messianic times. So
ועלהו לתרופה, Va-alehu li-trufa, the פסוק Pasuk says that this tree has
leaves, עלהו alehu the leaves, לתרופה, li-trufa, תרופה trufa is a medicine.
So what does this mean? רב חסדא ורב יצחק בר אבדימי. Rav
Chisda ve-Rav Yitzchak bar Avdimi. חד אמר להתיר פה של מעלה וחד
אמר להתיר פה של מטה. Chad amar le-hatir pe shel ma'ala ve-chad
amar le-hatir pe shel mata. One says that what does this magical
tree, what are the leaves, what are they good for medically? One
says it's for someone who is mute and this will allow him
to speak, to open his mouth. And the other says להתיר פה
של מטה le-hatir pe shel mata to open the lower mouth, in
other words a woman who is barren will be able to give
birth. איתמר, Itmar, wait could you say
again this is a מעין ma'ayan that comes...
It's a stream that comes out of the מקדש... Mikdash...
a מעין, ma'ayan, yeah...
or a spring then, yeah, a spring that comes out... from where?
From under
the קודש הקודשים Kodesh Hakodashim and it flows out from there. So
in other words it's a symbolic kind of thing that the מקדש
Mikdash is the source of water, healing, all that kind of stuff.
And here's a support for this. איתמר חזקיה אמר, Itmar Chizkiya amar,
חזקיה Chizkiya said, להתיר פה אלמים, le-hatir pe ilmim, this is the
same talking about the same פסוק Pasuk but we're more explicit. חזקיה
Chizkiya says this is to open the mouths of the dumb. בר
קפרא אמר להתיר פה עקרות. Bar Kappara amar le-hatir pe akarot. Bar
Kappara says these leaves are to open the womb of a barren
woman. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Now we're going back to the how
to make the חלות, Chalos, how to set up the
לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim on the table as we saw. You'll notice
that there's two stacks of six each. So that's what we have
to get to in the end. So let's first of all look
at the whole פסוק. Pasuk.
It says right here ולקחת סולת ואפית אותה שתים עשרה חלות. ve-lakachta
solet ve-afita otah shtem esrei chalot. You should take flour and bake
it into twelve loaves. שני עשרונים
יהיה החלה האחת. Shenei esronim yihye hachala ha-achat. Each חלה chala made
of two עשרונים, esronim, two measures of flour. As we said an
עישרון isaron is about a five-pound bag of flour. So these are
rather large loaves. And the next פסוק Pasuk is ושמת אותם שתים
מערכות. ve-samta otam shtayim ma'arachot. I'm reading from the side here where
it quotes the פסוק, Pasuk, ושמת אותם שתים מערכות, ve-samta otam shtayim
ma'arachot, and you should put them in two, we'll call them stacks,
שש המערכת, shesh hama'arechet, six in each stack, על השולחן הטהור לפני
השם, al hashulchan hatahor lifnei Hashem, on the pure table before God.
Okay,
so that's pretty straightforward, right? But the גמרא Gemara is going to
kind of analyze why we need every word to come out with
this, how we could have been misled. אילו נאמר, Ilu ne'emar, if
it had said ולקחת סולת ואפית אותה שתים עשרה חלות, ve-lakachta solet
ve-afita otah shtem esrei chalot, take flour and bake twelve חלות chalos
as it does say, ושמת אותם שתים מערכות, ve-samta otam shtayim ma'arachot,
and put them in two stacks, ולא נאמר שש, ve-lo ne'emar shesh,
and it didn't continue by saying שש המערכת, shesh hama'arechet, six in
each stack. So if it would have just said take twelve and
put them in two stacks, הייתי אומר אחת של ארבע ואחת של
שמונה, hayiti omer achat shel arba ve-achat shel shemona, that you would
have said okay it doesn't have to be six and six, could
be four and eight, could be three and seven. לכך נאמר שש,
Lekach ne'emar shesh, that's why the פסוק Pasuk continues שש המערכת, shesh
hama'arechet, six in each stack, six in a stack. It doesn't actually
'each' is an incorrect translation, six in a stack. Now ואילו נאמר
שתים מערכות שש המערכת ולא נאמר שתים עשרה, ve-ilu ne'emar shtayim ma'arachot
shesh hama'arechet ve-lo ne'emar shtem esrei,
and if it had not told us that there were twelve loaves
but it had just said two stacks, six in a stack, הייתי
אומר שלוש של שש שש, hayiti omer shalosh shel shesh shesh, I
would have thought that means שתים מערכות, shtayim ma'arachot, there are two
stacks, שש המערכת, shesh hama'arechet, and another stack of six. In other
words a total of three stacks of six.
So that's why it has to specify there are twelve loaves and
that way I know when it says six in a stack. means
six in each of the stacks I just referred to. וכך נאמר
שתים עשרה, Vekach ne'emar shteim esrei, that's why it specifies 12. ואילו
נאמר שתים עשרה חלות ומערכות, Ve-ilu ne'emar shteim esrei challot uma'arachot,
and if it had just said there are 12 loaves in stacks,
ולא נאמר שתים ושש, velo ne'emar shtayim vasheish, and it hadn't told
me there were two stacks of six, but it just said there
are 12 in stacks, הייתי אומר שלושה של ארבע ארבע, hayiti omer
sheloshah shel arba arba, maybe there are three stacks of four. I
know that there are 12, it says 12, but that could be
three stacks of four. לכך נאמר שתים ושש. Le-kach ne'emar shtayim vasheish.
That's why it says there are 12 loaves, two stacks, six in
a stack.
So the גמרא Gemara says הא עד שלא יאמרו ג' מקראות הללו
לא למדנו. Ha ad shelo yomeru gimel mikra'ot hallalu lo lamadnu.
If it hadn't said all three things, all those three details, we
wouldn't have known exactly how to do it. הכיצד? Ha-keitzad? So now
that we do have those three things, what's the, how do we
do it? נותן שתי מערכות של שש שש. Noten shtei ma'arachot shel
sheish sheish. So now we know that you have two stacks of
six each. ואם נתן אחת של ארבע ואחת של שמונה לא עשה.
Ve-im natan achat shel arba ve-achat shel shmonah lo asah. And if
you did it wrong, if you did it four and eight, that's
no good.
That the שולחן shulchan doesn't allow it.
Well, if you could, if you built the frame,
oh, it's about building the frame, not the way you stack them.
I mean, there's only one
way, really, that you stack it. Right, right. Now that you have
the frame, there's only one way to stack it. That's right.
So this is very theoretical and, you know,
it's a typical גמרא Gemara construction
of
exploring every possible option.
Now what about שתים של שבע שבע? shtayim shel sheva sheva? What
if you had two stacks of seven each, so you have 14?
So within the 14 you have your 12 and you have the
two stacks of six, you just have one extra one on top.
רבי אומר רואין את העליונה כאילו אינה. Rabbi omer ro'in et ha-elyonah
ke-ilu einah. רבי Rabbi says okay, so you have two stacks of
six, so you put on a seventh one? Okay, that doesn't invalidate
the six before. Interesting, the גמרא Gemara doesn't raise the question of
בל תוסיף, bal tosif, that you can't add. You know, the classic
בל תוסיף bal tosif is five פרשיות parshiyot in
תפילין tefillin
or extra day of סוכות Sukkot or something about adding an extra
holiday.
I don't recall, but yeah,
sitting in the סוכה Sukkah after you...
well, that's the question that comes up with people who have the
custom on שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeret because of the second day of
יום טוב Yom Tov in חוץ לארץ.
Chutz La'aretz. Okay, okay.
But yes, but that is a question with regards to that. So
you know, I've never been able to figure this out and רב
דב Rav Dov has discussed this a couple of times also. And
it's really not clear. It seems like very few things
really qualify as בל תוסיף. bal tosif. In most cases, we say
okay, so you had something extra, it was extraneous to the מצווה
mitzvah itself. You had the six loaves and you put a seventh
one on top, the seventh one is nothing, כאילו אינה. ke-ilu einah.
As רבי Rabbi says, it's as if it's not there. Can you
translate the phrase בל תוסיף? bal tosif?
בל תוסיף Bal tosif means you're not permitted to add מצוות mitzvot
to the תורה. Torah.
Okay.
Or you can't take a letter, you can't add a letter, you
can't subtract.
Right, right. Or, you know, like four scrolls, four parchments in your
תפילין tefillin with the four paragraphs from the תורה Torah written on
it, what if you had a fifth one? So that's a classic
when the גמרא Gemara discusses this מצווה mitzvah of בל תוסיף bal
tosif of not adding, that's a classic example.
But how that's different than seven loaves of חלה, challah, like why
don't you just say over there, so you have the four, so
you had an extra one, so that's, you know, we'll ignore that
one and you still did the מצווה. mitzvah. I mean, it may
be true that you still did the מצווה mitzvah and
you still transgressed
the negative מצווה mitzvah of not adding,
which is another interesting question which I never thought about.
But anyway, I'm just digressing because I don't know why this, whether
or whether this would qualify as the transgression of בל תוסיף. bal
tosif. But anyway, רבי Rabbi says regardless of that, he's not addressing
that, he's just saying you have your six, so if you have
the seventh it's as if it's not there.
So the גמרא Gemara asks on that, והא בעינא ונתת על. Ve-ha
ba'ina venatata al. The פסוק pasuk says ונתת על המערכת לבונה זכה.
Venatata al hama'arechet levonah zachah. We've had this before: put on the
framework,
this framework that holds the bread, put frankincense on it. And the
גמרא's Gemara understanding that putting something on it means it has to
be directly on top of the stack of bread. So if you
have the seventh one in the way, then it's not on the
מצווה mitzvah bread, it's on the bread that is not part of
the מצווה. mitzvah.
Unless you put it on top of the six and then put
the seventh on top of the...
okay, well, I guess you could do that.
But it wouldn't make a lot of sense.
Yeah, like we're questioning the whole... like what if you do... then
you're implicitly recognizing what
you're doing is not so good.
So אמר ליה רב חסדא לרב המנונא, Amar lei Rav Chisda le-Rav
Hamnuna, that's רב חסדא Rav Chisda said to רב המנונא, Rav Hamnuna,
ואמרי לה רב המנונא לרב חסדא, ve-amri lah Rav Hamnuna le-Rav Chisda,
or some say רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna said to רב חסדא, Rav
Chisda, רבי לטעמיה, Rabbi le-ta'ameih, this is okay for רבי Rabbi because
he's consistent, דאמר על בסמוך, de-amar al besamuch, because he says that
על al on the לחם lechem doesn't mean on the מערכת, ma'arechet,
doesn't mean on directly, it means near. Because... so the גמרא Gemara
says... או אינו אלא על ממש? o eino ela al mamash?
How do you know, maybe it really means על ממש, al mamash,
directly on. גמרא Gemara answers, כשהוא אומר וסכות על הארון את הפרוכת,
k'shehu omer v'sachos al ha-aron es ha-paroches,
it says that you should spread the... on the ארון aron you
should you should put the פרוכת, paroches, the curtain that divides the
קודש הקודשים Kodesh HaKodashim from the rest of the... from the rest
of the היכל. Heichal. You should put a curtain on it. הוי
אומר על בסמוך, Hevei omer al bisamuch, so we know that the
פרוכת paroches did not go on, wasn't draped over the ארון. aron.
It was a curtain standing in between this space and this space
and yet it uses the word על, al, on. So clearly the
word על al can mean near, not directly on. So so it's
not a question for רבי. Rabbi. רבי Rabbi can easily say that
that
it doesn't you could... that's why he could say that the לבונה
levonah doesn't have to be directly on the מצוה mitzvah bread, that
if there's another loaf of bread in the way that is not
part of the מצוה mitzvah and you put the לבונה levonah on
that, you're okay.
But then I don't know if if you have a curtain can
it be as the ארון, aron, can you have a curtain that
goes this way and this way so that you're literally like the...
Go ahead, ask your question.
Does the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
on יום טוב Yom Tov can go like into this...
Ah, the way it worked was they actually had two curtains, at
least I'm not sure if it was the same in the משכן
Mishkan or the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, they were like this, so
so that the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol would walk through here and
come inside.
Wow. If
I
recall correctly.
But there wasn't anything, what about on the side? In other words,
if it was...
No, no, on the side was the walls, right? What we have
here is a square you know or a rectangular, this is the
whole משכן, Mishkan, right? And here is the curtain that divides the
היכל Heichal where the we had the שלחן, shulchan, the table and
the מזבח mizbeiach and the and the מנורה menorah and here is
the ארון aron behind the curtain. Right. This is the curtain we're
talking about, so these are walls. Okay.
Got it.
I got it. Yeah, thank you. All
right.
All right,
so the משנה Mishnah said, כל הכלים שבמקדש, Kol ha-keilim she-ba-mikdash, what
does it say about them? Oh yeah, the orientation. It said that
the... so here's our... this is gonna be our... this is gonna
be our משכן Mishkan or our מקדש Mikdash right here.
And this orientation is East and West and this is North and
South.
Okay. And this is the... this where it says תלמוד בבלי Talmud
Bavli here, that's where the the פרוכת paroches is, so this is
the היכל Heichal and this is the קודש הקודשים. Kodesh HaKodashim. This
is where the ארון aron stood and this is where the other
the other vessels stood.
And now how did we place those items? Let's say we have
our our שלחן, shulchan, okay? Do we place it like this or
like this? Which way was it oriented? So the משנה Mishnah said
everything was oriented in the direction of the same way as the
as the היכל Heichal itself, like this. In other words, oriented East-West.
תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, כל הכלים שבמקדש אורכן לאורכן של בית, kol
ha-keilim she-ba-mikdash orkan l'orkan shel bayis, they were all everything in there
was oriented the same way as the as the בית המקדש, Beis
HaMikdash, חוץ מארון, chutz mei-aron, except for the ארון, aron, שאורכו לרוחבו
של בית. she-orko l'rochbo shel bayis. The ארון aron was placed like
this, okay? The length of the ארון aron was oriented towards the
width of the of the קודש הקודשים. Kodesh HaKodashim.
וכך היה מונח, v'kach hayah munach, that's how it was placed, וכך
היו בדיו מונחים, v'kach hayu badav munachim, and that's how how its
rods were placed. So everything, all the כלים שבמקדש keilim she-ba-mikdash had
these rods by which they were carried.
And here is a picture of the ארון. aron. One second. Yeah.
Well
this is got a nice gold picture.
Is there a picture of the whole
משכן Mishkan
anywhere?
Gorgeous. Gorgeous. וכך היה בדיו מונחים
v'kach
hayah
badav munachim and so
were its... the
staves were... now actually, I'm unclear.
I
think what it's supposed to be saying is that the staves were
north- were
were East-West. One second. אורכו לרוחבו של בית. orko l'rochbo shel bayis.
Why why is that?
One sec.
Well, we're gonna see how we know that the that the rods
were on the sides of the of the ארון. aron. Okay, so
we'll see that in a minute. The גמרא Gemara will will try
to prove that. So so what does that mean? This is how
it was placed and this is how its rods were placed. מאי
קאמר? mai qamar? What does it mean? הכי קאמר, hachi qamar, this
is how... And ובדיו מנלן, ubadav minhalan, how do I know in
fact that the poles were placed
east-west? דתניא, detanya, as we have a ברייתא, braisa, ויאריכו
הבדים, vayarikhu habadim, the rods, ויאריכו, vayarikhu, they were
lengthwise. I don't think that's how you would translate it, but אורך
orech means the length. יכול לא יהו נוגעין בפרוכת, yachol lo yehu
nogin baparochet, and maybe you would think that they don't touch the
curtain, which is
here, and maybe you place it so they don't touch the curtain.
תלמוד לומר ויראו. talmud lomar veyera'u.
So let's look at this whole פסוק pasuk first. It's a פסוק
pasuk in מלכים Melachim describing
the construction of the first בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash by שלמה. Shlomo.
I'll read it here: ושמת שם את ארון העדות, vesamta sham et
aron ha'edut, you should place there the
ark, sorry, wrong פסוק. pasuk. ויאריכו הבדים, vayarikhu habadim, the poles stretched
out, ויראו ראשי הבדים מן הקדש, veyera'u rashei habadim min hakodesh, and
the heads of the rods were seen from the קודש kodesh from
this part of the room, על פני הדביר al pnei hadvir on
the, I don't know how to translate דביר, dvir, I forget. Wasn't
the דביר dvir the קודש קדשים? Kodesh Kodashim? Yeah, maybe you're right.
מן הקודש על פני הדביר. min hakodesh al pnei hadvir.
So the דביר dvir
was the inside.
Where is it? In מלכים א Melachim Aleph פרק ח פסוק ח.
perek chet pasuk chet. מלכים א Melachim Aleph ח ח. chet chet.
So anyway, so it's kind of contradictory. It says they're seen from
the קודש kodesh but they would not be seen. So how is
it seen and not seen? ויראו, veyera'u, they were seen. אי ויראו
יכול יהו מקרעין בפרוכת ויוצאין, i veyera'u yachol yehu mekarin baparochet veyotzin,
maybe you would tear a hole in the curtain so that you
could see the rod. תלמוד לומר לא יראו החוצה, talmud lomar lo
yera'u hachutza, but the פסוק pasuk then says they would not be
seen from the outside. הכיצד, hakeitzad, so how does this work?
Outside of what?
Outside of the קודש קדשים? Kodesh Kodashim? Yeah, okay, in other words
from here. ויראו. veyera'u.
So how does this work? דוחקין ובולטין בפרוכת, dochakin uvotin baparochet, they
kind of bump into the פרוכת. parochet.
You can put in דביר dvir there.
Thank you. He's looking it up in an actual book. דביר dvir
is,
it's actually kind of a technical term, so I don't know if
it translates. All right, we got text here. Yeah, מלכים א Melachim
Aleph ח ח. chet chet. מלכים א Melachim Aleph ח
ח.
chet
chet.
In
front of the Holy of Holies. Okay, yeah, קודש קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim,
that's what the דביר dvir is. All right,
and
Verizon and Motorola are translating this for us, but I think you're
right, the דביר dvir means the קודש קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim. In the
פיוטים piyutim it's used to refer to the מקדש Mikdash generally.
Anyway,
so they would poke into the curtain, right? If you have rods
poking into a curtain, so you can see where they stick out
even though you can't see the rods themselves.
From the inside? They were from the inside. Right, right, right. And
the curtain was on the outside. Exactly.
In the back we come back
and I'll let you know.
So like this, it's sticking out, but you can't see it.
Is it like the shape there underneath?
This is a curtain, this is the rod, and it's making an
indentation in the curtain, but you can't see it because it's behind
it. Right, that's what's going on here. דומים כשני דדי אשה domim
kishnei dadei isha
and they looked like two breasts. שנאמר צרור המור דודי לי shenemar
tzror hamor dodi li as it says in שיר השירים, Shir Hashirim,
my beloved is to me like a package of
מור, mor, which is an incense. בין שדי ילין, bein shadai yalin,
I keep it between my breasts. So remember that the only thing
you actually did in the קודש קדשים Kodesh Kodashim was on יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur, the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol would come in with
the incense, right? That's the מור. mor. And he would light it
up
in front of the ארון, aron, right? So the incense is between
the breasts. Right?
That's imagery, right?
Like if it was a fire or something.
Well, no, the whole thing was, I mean there was fire all
over the place. The מזבח mizbeach was fire, there was fire in
the קודש קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim.
Yeah, but you have to be careful not to- That's an
image of a female god.
I mean they're speaking about God having breasts.
Yes, exactly. And you put the מור mor in between
the breasts and yes.
Okay, good for רבקה. Rivka.
Well yeah, there, I mean look, שיר השירים Shir Hashirim is full
of that imagery of course, but here here it's very explicit.
Yeah, but we always say he.
I know we do.
Uh-huh. Yeah. Okay. ומינלן דבצדיה דארונא הוו יתבי? Uminlan d'vatzadei d'arona havu
yatvei?
How do you know that the בדים, badim, the rods, are on
the sides? Maybe they're on the short side, maybe they're on the
long side, maybe it should be like this, right? Because אי נימא
לאורכיה דארונא הוו יתבי? Iy neima l'urkeih d'arona havu yatvei? Maybe they
were on the long side? אמר רב יהודה: תרי גברי באמתא ופלגא
לא מסתגי. Amar Rav Yehuda: Trei gavrei b'amta u'palga lo mistagei. You
can't fit two people in,
remember the dimensions of the ארון aron are two אמות amot by
one אמה, amah, or two... no,
two and a half by one and a half, right? אמתים וחצי
ארכו ואמה וחצי. Amataim v'chetzi orko v'amah v'chetzi. Yes, so this is
only one and a half אמות, amot, and if you're going to
put the poles here, what the גמרא Gemara is... you have a
pen? What the גמרא Gemara is
telling us here that we didn't know is that when you carry
these things, that there would be two people on each end within
the poles. So if this is only one and a half... thank
you, buddy. If this is only one and a half אמות, amot,
then there's not enough room for two people to stand there. So
it must be like this, so there's enough room for two people
to stand in two and a half אמות. amot.
Or does it mean one person in front, one person in back?
No, two people in front and two in back, as we'll see
in a minute.
How can they get into the back? There's enough space. I'm sorry?
There's enough room for two people to get behind...
I mean,
maybe they took it apart first, I don't know. Yeah.
Maybe they dismantled the building first and then took the things out,
I
don't know.
ומינלן דבארבעה הוו דרו ליה? Uminlan d'b'arba'ah havu daru leih?
How do we know it was just asked, how do you know
there were four people, two in the front and two in back,
or two on one side, two on the other? דכתיב: ונסעו הקהתים
נשאי המקדש. De'ketiv: U'nas'u ha'kehatim nosei ha'mikdash. נשאי... Nosei... תרי. trei. So
there's a plural. נשאי המקדש, Nosei HaMikdash, the carriers of the המקדש,
HaMikdash, which is assumed to be the ארון, aron, which is the
holiest thing in the place. So נשאי... nosei... תרי. trei. That's also
another two, so you have four people. So they must be... now
how do you know they're inside? I don't know how we know
that. Like maybe they would stand on the outside, right? But the
גמרא Gemara doesn't address that. It's just assuming it knows that the
two people stood inside. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Okay. Got that? So
now we know the orientation of everything. So far we've seen the
orientation of everything in the קדש Kodesh was east-west, and the ארון
aron was north-south,
with the poles being east-west. Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. עשרה שלחנות
עשה שלמה המלך.
Asarah shulchanot asah
Shlomo HaMelech.
When שלמה Shlomo built the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, he made ten
tables. שנאמר: ויעש שלחנות עשרה. She'ne'emar: Vaya'as shulchanot asarah. It says in
the פסוק pasuk he made ten tables. וינח בהיכל חמשה מימין וחמשה
משמאל. Vayanach ba'heichal chamishah mi'yamin v'chamishah mi'smol. And he put them in
the היכל, heichal, five on the
right and five on the left. ואם תאמר חמשה מימין הפתח וחמשה
משמאל הפתח. V'im tomar chamishah mi'yamin ha'petach v'chamishah mi'smol ha'petach. If... now
what do we mean by the right and the left? If you
think it means five over here and five over here... this is
the doorway, right? This is the entrance to the היכל. heichal. So
if you think it means five over here and five over here,
well, that can't be. Because והתורה אמרה: והשלחן תתן על צלע צפון.
V'ha'Torah amrah: V'hashulchan
titein al tzela tzafon.
The שלחן shulchan had to be on the north. So he couldn't
be putting any tables on the south. They all had to be
over here. So when it says to the right and left, it
means however you set them up here, and we'll discuss that in
detail, you know, five on the right, five on the left. In
other words, two rows of five. אלא של משה באמצע חמשה מימינו
וחמשה משמאלו.
Ela shel Moshe ba'emtza, chamishah mi'yimino
v'chamishah mi'smolo. So how
does it go? The original table of משה Moshe was in the
middle, חמשה מימינו וחמשה משמאלו, chamishah mi'yimino v'chamishah mi'smolo, five to the
right of משה's Moshe table and five to the left of משה's
Moshe table.
Why would they have so many tables?
We thought there was only one שלחן. shulchan. שלמה Shlomo was clearly
doing an elaborate job, right? I mean, you have the ceremony.
But now you're saying משה's Moshe had
five...
No, no, no. When it says there were five to the right
and five to the left, it means five to the right of
משה's Moshe table and five to the left of משה's Moshe table.
שלמה Shlomo made ten new tables, they still had the original של
משה.
shel Moshe. Yeah.
And we'll see in a minute that according to one opinion, the
other ones were just for show,
they didn't actually put...
well, there's... we'll see. The גמרא Gemara discusses whether they were used
or not. תנו רבנן: עשר מנורות עשה שלמה. Tanu Rabbanan: Esser menorot
asah Shlomo.
He also made ten מנורות. menorot. שנאמר: ויעש את מנרות הזהב עשר
כמשפט. She'ne'emar: Vaya'as et menorot ha'zahav esser kemishpat.
And he made as it says directly in the פסוק. pasuk. ויתן
בהיכל חמשה מימין וחמשה משמאל. Vayitein ba'heichal chamishah mi'yamin v'chamishah mi'smol. And
he put them in the היכל, heichal, five on the right and
five on the left. So the same thing: ואם תאמר חמשה מימין
הפתח וחמשה משמאל הפתח. V'im tomar chamishah mi'yamin ha'petach v'chamishah mi'smol ha'petach.
If you think that it means five on the right side of
the building and five on the left. אם כן מצינו מנורה בצפון.
Im kein matzinu menorah b'tzafon. Then that would mean that there were
some מנורות menorot on the north. והתורה אמרה: ואת המנורה נכח השלחן.
V'ha'Torah amrah: V'et ha'menorah nochach ha'shulchan. התורה Torah says that the מנורה
menorah has to be opposite the שלחן, shulchan, in other words on
the south. אלא של משה באמצע חמשה מימינו וחמשה משמאלו. Ela shel
Moshe ba'emtza, chamishah mi'yimino v'chamishah mi'smolo. So how does it go? You
had the original מנורה menorah in the middle, and when it says
right and left, it means to the right and left of משה's
Moshe מנורה. menorah. תני חדא. Tani chada.
We have one תנא tanna that says: מחצי הבית ולפנים היו מונחים.
Michatzi ha'bayit u'lifnim havu munachim. One says it was they were on
the, so on the inside half of the of the building, right,
in other words on the side. ותני חדא Vetani chada משליש הבית
ולפנים. meshlish habayit velifnim. They were from one third of the way
in. ולא קשיא Velo kashya and it's not contradictory. מר כחשיב בית
קדש קדשים בהדי היכל. Mar kachashiv beit kodesh kodashim bahadi heichal. One,
the one who says half means half of this whole area, right,
the קדש Kodesh and the קדש הקדשים, Kodesh Hakodashim, which was as
we'll see in a minute, forty and twenty. Right, so half of
forty plus twenty is forty plus twenty is sixty and so halfway
is thirty. So they were all within this line. ומר סבר, Umarsavar,
the one that, I'm sorry, the third, the one who says a
third says they're all, what's a third of sixty? Twenty. So they're
all within the twenty yard line. Okay. And the football is, right.
ומר לא כחשיב
בית קדש הקדשים.
Umarlo kachashiv
beit kodesh hakodashim.
The one who says halfway, he's only talking about this, the first
room, the קדש Kodesh which is forty and halfway to that is
again the twenty yard line. So they're both saying the same thing,
just from a different perspective. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. מזרח ומערב היו
מונחים, Mizrach uma'arav hayu munachim, דברי רבי. divrei rebbi. They were placed,
now we're talking about the orientation again. So our משנה Mishnah said
they were oriented east-west and that's what רבי Rebbi says. רבי אלעזר
ברבי שמעון אומר צפון ודרום. Rebbi Elazar berabbi Shimon omer tzafon vedarom.
Rebbi Elazar ben Shimon says they were oriented north-south. Not like our
משנה. Mishnah. מאי טעמא דרבי. Mai ta'ama deRebbi. How does רבי Rebbi
know? גמר, Gamar, and I think we're talking about the שולחן Shulchan
here. גמר ממנורה. Gamar mimenorah. He learns it from the מנורה. Menorah.
מה מנורה מזרח ומערב, Ma Menorah mizrach uma'arav, just as I know
the מנורה Menorah was east-west, we'll see how he knows that in
a minute, אף הני נמי מזרח ומערב. af hanei nami mizrach uma'arav.
So the tables were also arranged east-west. ומנורה גופה מנלן. Umenorah gufa
minalan. How do you know the מנורה Menorah itself was east-west? מדכתיב
בנר מערבי יערך אותו אהרן לפני ה'. midechtiv bener ma'aravi ya'aroch oto
Aharon lifnei Hashem. There is,
now it doesn't actually say in the תורה Torah that there was
a western lamp, okay, but we all know that there was one
of the, well the תורה Torah does say one of the lamps
was the main one, that was the one that stayed lit all
day where the other ones went out. Right, yeah, right. So that
is the western one.
Now, if there's a western one, a western lamp, that means it
must be oriented east-west, right? Because if they were oriented north-south, they're
all equally close to the west. So it must be it's oriented
east-west and the western lamp is the western lamp, at least according
to רש"י. Rashi. The western one is the western one. תוספות Tosafot
actually says that the western one is
the first one to the west of the eastern one, in other
words the second one from the east.
As you go west, it's the first one you encounter after the
first. It's a little convoluted, but anyway, but רש"י Rashi says it's
the western one so we'll stick with that.
So since there is a western lamp, so we know the מנורה
Menorah was oriented east-west and therefore the שולחן, Shulchan, which is נוכח
המנורה, nocheach hamenorah, which is opposite the מנורה Menorah is also oriented
the same way. מכלל דכולהו לאו לפני ה'. michlal dechulho lav lifnei
Hashem. In other words, yeah, this is so we know that they
were all, not all of the lamps were equally לפני ה', lifnei
Hashem, only the one that was on the west side. ואי סלקא
דעתך צפון ודרום, Ve'isalka dachatch tzafon vedarom, and if you think it's
oriented north-south, כולהו נמי לפני ה' נינהו, kulho nami lifnei Hashem ninhu,
they're all equally close to the west, close to the קדש הקדשים.
Kodesh Hakodashim.
So it was almost saying ה' Hashem is in the קדש? kodesh?
Yeah, we've seen this several times before, that לפני ה' lifnei Hashem
means closer to the קדש הקדשים, Kodesh Hakodashim, right, or to the
holier part from where you are. If you're outside, then this is
לפני ה', lifnei Hashem, right? Like we talked about the door, the
outside מזבח mizbe'ach being close to the door to the closest thing
to the entrance of the קדש. kodesh.
רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון. Rebbi Elazar berabbi Shimon. So how about רבי
אלעזר ברבי שמעון? Rebbi Elazar berabbi Shimon? How does he say that
it's north-south? מאי טעמא. Mai ta'ama. Why does he say it's north-south?
גמר מארון. Gamar me'aron. He learns it from the ארון. Aron. מה
ארון צפון ודרום, Ma aron tzafon vedarom, we just saw that the
ארון aron was oriented north-south, אף הני נמי צפון ודרום. af hanei
nami tzafon vedarom. So these the מנורה Menorah was also north-south. ורבי
נמי ליגמר מארון. Verebbi nami ligmar me'aron. So why doesn't רבי Rebbi
compare it to the ארון? aron? דנין חוץ מחוץ ואין דנין חוץ
מבפנים. Danin chutz michutz ve'ein danin chutz mibifnim. Because the ארון aron
was you know inside the קדש הקדשים, Kodesh Hakodashim, the מנורה Menorah
was in the קדש, Kodesh, so let's you know let's derive it
from something that is closer to it which is the שולחן, Shulchan,
rather than from the ארון. aron. So רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון ליגמר
ממנורה. Rebbi Elazar berabbi Shimon ligmar mimenorah. So that's a good point,
so why doesn't רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rebbi Elazar berabbi Shimon insist
on on comparing the מנורה Menorah to the orientation of the מנורה
Menorah to the ארון? aron? Why doesn't he compare it to the
שולחן? Shulchan? אמר לך מנורה גופא צפון ודרום הוה מנחא. Amar lach
Menorah gufa tzafon vedarom hava mancha.
He'll tell you
that
the מנורה, Menorah, I'm sorry we're talking about the שולחן, Shulchan, so
why doesn't he learn from the שולחן Shulchan which we're assuming to
have been east-west?
So he says no, the מנורה Menorah was also north-south. Indeed, the
שולחן Shulchan was the same as the מנורה Menorah and it was
also north-south. So now רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rebbi Elazar berabbi Shimon
is turning everything on its head.
Now he's putting them both oriented, yeah, I just said that right,
he's putting them both
oriented
north-south. Yeah. אלא הכתיב יערוך אותו אהרון ובניו. Ella HaKetiv Yaroch Oto
Aharon Ubanav.
So what about the idea of of the one of the lamps
was was לפני השם, Lifnei HaShem, it was more more westerly? So
how do how do you understand that if there was a north-south
orientation? Gemara answers דמצדדי להו אצדודי. DeMitzadadi Lehu Itzdudei.
It's the it's the way that you that you lean the wicks
over.
And it says like יערוך. Yaroch. You know, when you look at
this picture, they go יערוך, Yaroch,
set up I guess, with an ayin. Right. Yeah. Yeah. There's two
different.
Okay, yeah, there's a good picture also.
Right.
The wicks are pointing towards the center, except for the center one
which is pointing towards the west. Okay, and actually the way that
the picture sets it up is that there's a little indentation towards
the center. Oh yeah. But this one has the indentation towards the
side towards the west. Oh. You see that's where the wick would
would lean out.
That's what I didn't
understand how it was going to work for that bottom
one.
דתניא, DeTanya, as we learned in a brayta, אל מול פני המנורה
יאירו שבעת הנרות, El Mul Pnei HaMenorah Yairu Shivat HaNerot, the the
the
seven lamps shone towards the face, the surface or the face of
the Menorah. What does that mean? מלמד שהיו מצדדים פניהם כלפי נר
אמצעי. Melamed Shehayu Metzadedim Pneihem Klapei Ner Emtzai. They all lean towards
the middle lamp. אמר רבי נתן, Amar Rabbi Natan, אמר רבי נתן,
Amar Rabbi Natan,
thank you, מכאן שאמצעי משובח. Mikan She'emtzai Meshubach.
From here we see that the middle one was the
best one.
Okay, the main one.
Whatever the middle one is the best.
Yeah, well, you know, it's part of the center column, right? Remember
there's the center column and then the other ones branch out from
it.
So now Gemara asks בשלמא למאן דאמר מזרח ומערב. Bishlama Leman De'amar
Mizrach U'maarav. Okay,
so if you're going to say it's oriented east-west, היינו דהוו יתבי
עשרה בעשרין. Hainu Dehavu Yatvei Asara B'Esrin. Now here we're getting back
to the the how it fits in the space. היינו דהוו יתבי
עשרה בעשרין. Hainu Dehavu Yatvei Asara B'Esrin. Now remember we just said
that if we're only counting the 40 the 40 amot here in
the Kodesh and it had to be within the back 20, right?
halfway. So we have 20 amot that the Shulchan and now there
are actually 11 Shulchanot have to fit in. Well, so there's two
rows of five and one in the middle. Moshe's is in the
middle, then you have two rows of five. Okay? Now, if they're
oriented east-west and the table is how what are the dimensions 1x2,
right? So there's five there's five
tables
each one two amot long, so that's 10 amot and you have
a space of 20, so you're good. Right? So בשלמא למאן דאמר
מזרח ומערב.
Bishlama Leman
De'amar Mizrach U'maarav. So if that's good if they're facing east-west, היינו
דהוו יתבי עשרה בעשרין, Hainu Dehavu Yatvei Asara B'Esrin, that you have
you have 10 amot because five a row of five tables each
one is two is 10 amot בעשרין B'Esrin in the space of
20. אלא למאן דאמר צפון ודרום, Ella Leman De'amar Tzafon U'darom, if
you're saying they're oriented north-south,
so this is also 20 amot, but remember the Menorah had to
be on one side on the was it the north or south,
I can't remember again. Okay, let's say it's the south side. So
that's 10 amot of space, right? And now you have five tables
times two amot each, that's 10 amot right there. למאן
דאמר צפון ודרום יוד בכף היכי הוו יתבי? Leman De'amar Tzafon U'darom
Yud B'Kaf Heichi Havu Yatvei?
How could you fit
10 no wait a minute. What's the problem here? היינו דהוו יתבי
עשרה בעשרין.
Hainu Dehavu Yatvei Asara
B'Esrin. עשרה בעשרין עשרה בעשרין עשרה בעשרין עשרה
בעשרין עשרה בעשרין.
Asara B'Esrin Asara B'Esrin Asara
B'Esrin
Asara B'Esrin
Asara B'Esrin.
I'm not sure how
to
read this exactly. I mean I see what the problem is but
I'm not sure how to read it. One second let me see
what it says
here.
Oh,
so he tries to how can how can 10 two amot tables
rest in precisely 20 amot of space?
Right. But two and furthermore, כוהנים היכא הוו אזלי, kohanim heicha havo
azlei, how could the כוהנים kohanim
go
through if they were if they would run they'd be running wall
to wall? וטו v'tu and furthermore,
שולחן דמשה היכא מנח ליה, shulchan d'Moshe heicha manach lei, where was
משה's Moshe שולחן? shulchan? No before that.
מצינו חמשה שולחנות בדרום, matzinu chamisha shulchanot b'darom, you'd have five in
the in the north. So we're assuming that there's just one long
row of tables that would it would have to stretch all the
way across so you couldn't walk through. Where was משה's Moshe table,
right?
Oh yeah, cause we were saying like to the right and the
left. So five to the right, five to the left in a
row, but that covers the whole thing and there's nowhere in the
middle for משה's Moshe table.
I'm already thinking of the answer that's why I didn't see the
question.
ולטעמיך u'l'tamecha and furthermore, למאן דאמר מזרח ומערב נמי שולחן דמשה היכא
מנח ליה. l'man d'amar mizrach u'maarav nami shulchan d'Moshe heicha manach lei.
אלא, ella, אלא ella the גמרא Gemara answers מי סברת חד דרא
הוו, mi savrat chad dara havo, how do you know they were
all in one row? תרי דרי הוו, trei darei havo, they were
in two rows, five and five. So five times two אמה amma
is only ten אמות ammas and you can fit that within twenty
אמות. ammas. So you had here's a great picture in the Artscroll.
This is the
this is the so the east-west orientation is easy. Page 98. 98b5.
Yeah.
So the so according to רבי Rabbi it's east-west, no problem.
According to רבי אלעזר בן שמעון Rabbi Elazar ben Shimon there's five
and five and there's משה's Moshe in the middle. Why in the
middle? Right.
Do we ever find out what went on the other tables? Yes,
we will find out.
What
about the other מנורות? menorot? Oh yeah, I don't think maybe I
didn't get far enough in the גמרא Gemara but I didn't see
nothing else was on the other מנורות menorot or tables. So that's
on צדי טית עמוד א, tzadi tet amud aleph, 99a. בשלמא למאן
דאמר צפון ודרום שפיר. bishlama l'man d'amar tzafon v'darom shapir.
So according now if you say they ran north-south then fine, so
you have five and five, you have plenty of room. אלא למאן
דאמר מזרח ומערב, ella l'man d'amar mizrach u'maarav, now we're going to
ask about the one the one that says it was oriented east-west,
מכדי, michdi, let's see how this works. שולחן כמה משוך מן הכותל
שתי אמות ומחצה. shulchan kama mashuch min hakotel shtei amot u'mechtza. The
table had to be that we're talking about this wall, okay, the
table so you had we're going to have two rows of five
tables each. Okay, but what about the the width? It had to
be within the north side so south side? Yeah,
north side. So let's see if there's enough space because it couldn't
be right next to the wall because the גמרא Gemara is assuming
that just as just as two people carried the ארון, aron, remember
that? So part of the ceremony of placing and removing the bread,
two כוהנים kohanim walk side by side with the I guess with
each with the six loaves or something. So you need two and
a half אמות amot just like we had here, two and a
half אמות amot you need between the table and the wall for
them to walk. So you got two and a half, then the
then the table itself was one אמה amma wide. Then another two
and a half between that and the next row so now we're
up to six. Seven and another two and a half... Oh no,
we have the משה's Moshe table in the middle.
Right. So now we have two and a half and one is
three and a half, another two and a half is
six, seven, nine and a half, ten and a half. Okay, so
now we're sticking out so
now that's how the גמרא Gemara is going to describe it. אלא
למאן דאמר מזרח ומערב מכדי, ella l'man d'amar mizrach u'maarav michdi, let's
see how this is done. שולחן כמה משוך מן הכותל שתי אמות
ומחצה, shulchan kama mashuch min hakotel shtei amot u'mechtza, it has to
be two and a half אמות amot away from the wall. ואמה
דידיה, v'amma didei, and an אמה amma wide. ושתי אמות ומחצה דביני
ביני, u'shtei amot u'mechtza d'beini beini, and two and a half אמות
amot between משה's Moshe table. ואמה, v'amma,
and then there's another אמה. amma. ושתי אמות ומחצה דביני ביני, u'shtei
amot u'mechtza d'beini beini, another two and a half אמות amot between
משה's Moshe table and the next row. ואמה דידיה, v'amma didei, and
its אמה. amma. אשתכח דקא פליג לשולחן פלגא דאמתא בדרום, ishtakach d'ka
palig l'shulchan palga d'amta b'darom,
so we're a half half an אמה amma over the the dividing
line, half of the last row of tables is in the wrong
side, is on the south side of the משכן. mishkan. So what
about that?
So the גמרא Gemara says לא, lo, not so, דמדלי ליה ומנח
ליה ומיטתי ליה ופורתא. d'madlei lei u'manach lei u'mitatei lei u'purta.
The table of משה Moshe was not directly in the middle, it
was more like this. I think there's a picture in here also.
Okay, so you didn't need a full two and a half אמות
amot between these could be closer because this was not directly between
the two rows it was up here.
Why
was the table named after משה? Moshe?
Oh, it was made by משה. Moshe. Oh, it was made by
בצלאל, Bezalel, by I guess from the one that משה Moshe was
commanded to make. Yeah, good question. Here, yeah, the 99A1 has the
diagram, right? See here, you have the two rows of the table
and then the table of משה Moshe was up here near to
the front. כתלמיד היושב לפני רבו, k'talmid hayoshev lifnei rabo,
like a student sitting before the teacher. In other words, the table
of משה Moshe is the teacher and the two rows of students
sitting at his feet.
But what's the function the משה Moshe table had?
That was the one that they will see. The question is what
was the function of the other one. Table of משה Moshe was
the main one, that was where the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim was
put on every week. The question is what was the function of
the other ones, so we'll see whether they were just for decoration
or whether they also had bread on them.
תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan,
עשרה שולחנות עשה שלמה, asarah shulchanos asah Shlomo,
שלמה Shlomo made ten tables, ולא היו מסדרין אלא על של משה.
v'lo hayu mesadrin ela al shel Moshe. This is the question, they
would only put the bread on the table of משה, Moshe, שנאמר,
shene'emar, ואת השולחן אשר עליו לחם הפנים זהב. v'es hashulchan asher alav
lechem hapanim zahav.
It says in מלכים, Melachim, refers to the table singular which had
the לחם הפנים. lechem hapanim. So the other ten tables that שלמה
Shlomo made were just for ornamentation. They were not used for anything.
עשרה מנורות עשה שלמה, asara menoros asah Shlomo, שלמה Shlomo made ten
מנורות, menoros, ולא היו מדליקין אלא בשל משה. v'lo hayu madlikin ela
beshel Moshe. We'll talk about this. They did not light them, only
lit the one of משה, Moshe, שנאמר, shene'emar, את מנורת הזהב ונרותיה
לבער בערב. es menoras hazahav v'neroseha leva'er ba'erev. Refers to the מנורה
menora in the singular that they lit.
So the other ten were again just for ornamentation. רבי אלעזר בן
שמוע אומר, Rabbi Elazar ben Shamua omer, על כולם היו מסדרין. al
kulam hayu mesadrin. No, רבי אלעזר בן שמוע Rabbi Elazar ben Shamua
says no, they would put the bread, they would put bread on
all ten, all eleven tables, שנאמר, shene'emar, את השולחנות ועליהם לחם הפנים.
es hashulchanos va'aleihem lechem hapanim. Another
פסוק pasuk says in the plural, the tables with the with the
לחם הפנים lechem hapanim on it. ובכולן היו מדליקין, uv'kulan hayu madlikin,
and they would also light all the מנורות, menoros, שנאמר, shene'emar, את
המנורות ונרותיהם לבערם. es hamenoros v'neroseihem leva'aram. It also says in the
plural that the מנורות menoros plural.
And these פסוקים pesukim are from דברי הימים. Divrei Hayamim. Okay, so
it's not the only place where there's different versions of things in
מלכים Melachim and דברי הימים. Divrei Hayamim.
Do we know when רבי אלעזר בן שמוע Rabbi Elazar ben Shamua
lived, what state?
Well we, in certain, me, I don't know.
He was a תנא, tanna, right?
Yeah, he's a תנא. tanna. Yeah, רבי Rabbi is a תנא, tanna,
right. No, no, רבי Rabbi means from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael or
בבל. Bavel. I don't know.
Okay, I don't know either.
But anyway, we're talking about the first בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash in
the פסוקים, pesukim, right? It's not, we're not addressing how many they
had in the second. That's true, שלמה, Shlomo, yeah. So nobody would
have remembered what was there.
Well they would have kept them, one would assume.
One assumes, but I'm not so sure. There's only one on the
Arch of Titus, right? Yeah.
Some
say there are, there are ten more buried
under the, under
the Temple Mount.
Exactly, yeah, or in the Vatican Library or somewhere. Right. We say
there is also, רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yose bar Rabbi
Yehuda omer, לא היו מסדרין אלא על של משה. lo hayu mesadrin
ela al shel Moshe. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose bar Rabbi
Yehuda says no, it was only,
the bread was only on the table of משה. Moshe. אלא מה
אני מקיים, ela mah ani mekayem, את השולחנות אשר עליהם לחם הפנים
זהב? es hashulchanos asher aleihem lechem hapanim zahav? So what does it
mean in דברי הימים Divrei Hayamim when it says tables plural? So
this is what we're talking about. אלו שלושה שולחנות שהיו במקדש. elu
sheloshah shulchanos shehayu baMikdash. There were three functional tables in the מקדש.
Mikdash. שניים שהיו באולם מבפנים לפתח הבית. shenayim shehayu ba'ulam mifnim lepesach
habayis.
There were two that were out here in what's called the אולם,
ulam, it's outside of the, the קודש, Kodesh, outside of the היכל,
Heichal, but this is like the, where the, where the outer מזבח
mizbe'ach was. And there were two tables there, we'll see what they
were used for in a minute. אחד של כסף ואחד של זהב,
echad shel kesef v'echad shel zahav, one silver and one gold. על
של כסף נותן לחם הפנים בכניסתו. al shel kesef nosein lechem hapanim
bichnisaso.
On the silver one, you, the silver table out here, you would
put down the bread when you go in, right? Because remember you
have to do an exchange here. You have to take the new
bread and replace the old bread. So it sounds like what they
would do is, have a silver table here, put the bread on
it, the fresh bread on it, go in here, remove the old
bread, ועל של זהב ביציאתו, v'al shel zahav biyitziaso, and take that
bread and put it on the gold table out here while you're
then bringing this in and putting it on the inside table.
Count the space.
Right. So that's why, that's why it refers to three functional table,
or plural functional tables in דברי הימים. Divrei Hayamim. It's not talking
about the ten ceremonial ones that שלמה Shlomo made, it's talking about
the two functional ones that were out here.
Now I don't know what he's going to say about the מנורה
menorah though, but I don't think, I'm not sure if we get
to that.
מעלין בקודש ולא מורידין. ma'alin bakodesh v'lo moridin.
So the bread that comes in doesn't go into the gold, it
goes into the silver as opposed to the bread that's been in
the gold
goes onto the gold?
But since it's, it seems to
me once it's not the
same, it should go, it should be empty and should go into
the silver and gold should
Well, that's what the
גמרא Gemara deals with, it was going to discuss that question right
now,
and why do you do it that way? ויהבי ליה בטנא של
כסף שמעלין בקודש ולא מורידין. v'yahavi leh b'tene shel kesef shema'alin bakodesh
v'lo moridin. Because
with קודש kodesh things, you you want to always be ascending. So
gold is more valuable than silver, so you put it on the
silver first and then the gold. Okay.
Okay.
So
they thought that gold was more precious than...
Yeah, I understand that part, but I'm assuming once it's being removed,
it still has that high sanctified value and it seems to me
it can stay there, it's not fresh, that's why I was thinking
it's still going to the silver.
Oh yeah, but you don't you don't demote it.
The גמרא Gemara
is going to continue with this idea in a little bit. Actually
so actually interesting because there's there's two ways you can understand, it
seems to me there's two ways you can understand מעלין בקודש ואין
מורידין ma'alin bakodesh v'ein moridin that you go up, and one is
that if you have an object that was used for a holy
purpose, then you can only use that object for a more holy
purpose, not a less holy purpose, right? So for example, it's I
think I'm not sure what status this has really in הלכה halacha
or if it's just customary, but if you have a שול, shul,
you can't make it into a church, right?
Right, there's a whole hierarchy of
what you can sell things and a ספר תורה...
Sefer Torah...
Right,
although you can make a church and make it into a שול.
shul.
Right. So we're talking about the object itself, that's probably not such
a good example, but whatever. But but then there's the other thing
of how you treat the object, right? You treat it with, you
know, you put it on gold after silver but not on silver
after gold.
Right.
Like if you have a ספר תורה Sefer Torah that's פסול, pasul,
you can if you want to cut out a piece, you can't
put it into a מזוזה, mezuzah, you might be able to put
it to replace another ספר... isn't there something about that? You can't...
Yeah, so I'm not up on all the details, but I think
there's two ways you can understand the level of קדושה. Even if
it's פסול, pasul, you still have to treat
it in a way...
Right. So what happened to that bread? It's said a day old...
Eaten by the כהנים Kohanim and it was a week old but
miraculously it stayed warm and fresh.
Yeah, you missed that part, they would bring it out and it
would still be hot and everyone... it was a miracle.
I wonder once they took it home though if they had
to eat it...
You realize they couldn't take it home, they had to eat it
there. Eaten there. Yeah. And they said they couldn't share with their...
I didn't realize they were more advanced then than we are now.
Take a loaf of bread home and...
Hubris. Okay.
This is a great, this is a great גמרא. Gemara.
Wow. ומנלן... u'minalan... sorry... מעלין בקודש ולא מורידין, ma'alin bakodesh v'lo moridin,
that's what...
Right. ומנלן דמעלין בקודש ולא מורידין.
u'minalan d'ma'alin bakodesh
v'lo moridin.
So אחד של זהב בפנים שעליו לחם הפנים תמיד,
echad shel zahav bifnim
she'alav
lechem hapanim tamid,
and of course there was the gold table inside that had the
לחם הפנים lechem hapanim on it. ומנלן דאין מורידין, u'minalan d'ein moridin,
how do you know that you don't lower the status of a
holy object? דאמר רבי דאמר קרא ויקם משה את המשכן ויתן את
אדניו וישם את קרשיו ויתן את בריחיו ויקם את עמודיו. d'amar Rabbi
d'amar kra vayakem Moshe et hamishkan vayiten et adanav vayasem et krashav
vayiten et brichav vayakem et amudav. So it's totally unclear how this
פסוק, pasuk, which means Moshe erected the משכן mishkan and he placed
the the base things and he he placed the pillars
and he placed the בריחים, brichim, the the rod the internal rods,
and he erected the עמודים, amudim, no the עמודים amudim are the
pillars. So there's
like several very unsatisfactory explanations of how this shows...
how this shows דאין מורידין.
d'ein moridin.
One is that the לשון lashon ויקם, vayakem, which is a more
elevated thing, he erected rather than placed, is is
used
at the end. I don't know, it it doesn't make any sense
to me. None of the explanations made any sense to me, so
I I don't know what to say here about this proof.
But if you want to see in the ArtScroll, maybe some of
it will make sense to you, that's where I that's where I
saw some of the explanations. ומנלן דמעלין, u'minalan d'ma'alin, but this one
makes more sense,
how do we know that you do you are supposed to go
up a level? אמר רבי יוחנן בר יעקב דאמר קרא את מחתות
החטאים האלה בנפשותם, amar Rabbi Yochanan bar Yaakov d'amar kra et machtot
hachata'im ha'eleh b'nafshotam, talking about the the fire pans of the people
in the rebellion of קרח, Korach, they were all 250 of them
told to take fire pans of incense and bring them into the
משכן mishkan and see what would happen. So and of course they
all got destroyed, they all got burned, so God said to משה,
Moshe, take those pans which were used inappropriately,
ועשו אותם ריקועי פחים ציפוי למזבח כי הקריבום לפני ה' ויקדשו
v'asu otam riku'ei pachim tzipui lamizbeach ki
hikrivum lifnei Hashem vayikdashu
because they've already been... been
brought before God, so they've become holy, ויהיו לאות לבני ישראל, v'yihyu
le'ot livnei Yisrael, and let them be a sign to בני ישראל.
Bnei Yisrael. בתחילת תשמישי מזבח, b'tchilat tashmishei mizbeach, first they were they
were the כלים keilim for the מזבח, mizbeach, they were the, you
know, the vessels used for the מזבח. mizbeach. ועכשיו גופו של מזבח,
v'achshav gufo shel mizbeach, and now they're becoming part of the actual
מזבח mizbeach itself as an overlay to the מזבח. mizbeach. Very powerful.
מכאן לתלמיד חכם, mican l'talmid chacham, מכאן לתלמיד חכם ששכח תלמודו מחמת
אונסו. mican l'talmid chacham sheshachach talmudo machmat onso. From here we see
that a תלמיד חכם— talmid chacham wait you skipped, you skipped. Oh
sorry. Oh sorry yes I did. אשר שברת. asher shibarta. אשר שברת
ושמתם בארון. asher shibarta v'samtem ba'aron. Here's another, well
here's another proof of the same thing. You take the broken לוחות
luchot and put them in the in the ark. Even though they're
broken. Right. תני רב יוסף. tani Rav Yosef. רב יוסף Rav Yosef
says, מלמד שהלוחות ושברי לוחות מונחים בארון. melamed shehaluchot v'shivrei luchot munachim
ba'aron. It teaches us that both the second לוחות luchot and the
broken pieces of the first לוחות luchot were in the ark. מכאן
לתלמיד חכם ששכח תלמודו מחמת אונסו. mican l'talmid chacham sheshachach talmudo machmat
onso. From here we see that a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham who
forgets his his learning, not from neglect but from, you know, health
or whatever, declining powers of memory, שאין נוהגים בו מנהג ביזיון. she'ein
nohagim bo minhag bizayon. You cannot treat him with disdain. He still
has to be treated with status. So this isn't directly related to
מעלין בקודש ואין מורידין. ma'alin bakodesh v'ein moridin. Well I guess it
is, it's another form of מעלין בקודש ואין מורידין. ma'alin bakodesh v'ein
moridin. And that is where we will stop
for today.
Thank you Dov.
Thank you.
What
a what a lot of responsibility.
You did a great job.
I did.